<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Thomas Broadley]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Blog posts by Thomas Broadley.]]></description>
        <link>https://thomasbroadley.com</link>
        <image>
            <url>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/rss.png</url>
            <title>Thomas Broadley</title>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com</link>
        </image>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 14:23:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <copyright><![CDATA[2020 Thomas Broadley]]></copyright>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <managingEditor><![CDATA[Thomas Broadley]]></managingEditor>
        <webMaster><![CDATA[Thomas Broadley]]></webMaster>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My goals for RC]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
This week I’m participating in a <a href="https://www.recurse.com">Recurse Center</a> mini-batch. RC had been on my radar for a while, but an old coworker of mine encouraged me to apply recently. Here are my goals for the week.
</p>

<h2>
  Blog everyday
</h2>

<p>
  I haven’t blogged as much as I’d like to in the past few months. RC is a good opportunity to get back into the habit. I’ll follow the example of a few folks I’ve seen on RC’s <a href="https://blaggregator.recurse.com/about/">Blaggregator</a> and post daily about what I’ve been working on. It seems like a good way to stay accountable to myself, celebrate my progress, and build memories of my time at RC.
</p>

<h2>
  Pair everyday
</h2>

<p>
  I’ve found out that I prefer coding alone and getting as little feedback as necessary, partly because I don’t take criticism well. I think this is a mistake. I could produce higher-quality work and grow more quickly if I collaborated more. So this week I’m going to do at least one pairing session with another Recurser per day. Maybe if I pair more regularly I’ll internalize that it’s more productive than working alone.
</p>

<h2>
  Do a talk
</h2>

<p>
  I found out that Recursers give talks on technical subjects every Friday evening. I’m going to give one to practice public speaking and to encourage myself to dive deeply into at least one topic while I’m at RC.
</p>

<h2>
  Have fun!
</h2>

<p>
  Modulo the goals above, I won’t force myself to do anything I don’t enjoy. Instead I’m going to follow my nose, work on things that interest me, and switch it up if I’m not having fun. This week I want to nurture my curiosity about computer science and my intrinsic motivation to program. If I start something interesting and give up halfway through, I can always pick it back up after RC.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/my-goals-for-rc/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">my-goals-for-rc</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Brushing my teeth]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  For a long time, my poor oral health has frustrated me and stressed me out. My attitude has been that, since I brush and floss regularly, it doesn’t make sense that my gums are inflamed and receding.
</p>

<p>
  I’ve realized that, when I say it doesn’t make sense, I mean it’s unfair. I put effort into oral hygiene and I don’t get the outcomes that my dentist promised. But fairness doesn’t matter. What matters is whether my teeth are healthy or not.
</p>

<p>
  So I’m committing to taking care of my mouth in ways that actually keep it healthy. (For example, I don’t brush my teeth methodically, which likely contributes to tartar build-up. Mindfulness while brushing is the solution.) And I’ll try to avoid this in other areas of my life. No more feeling sorry for myself while forgetting about the reality of the situation!
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/brushing-my-teeth/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">brushing-my-teeth</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PipedInputStream and PipedOutputStream gotchas]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  To do I/O in Java, you read from InputStreams and write to OutputStreams. Sometimes you want to connect the output of an OutputStream to the input of an InputStream. In my case, I wanted to upload a CSV (generated by writing to a given OutputStream) to Amazon S3 (using a class reading from an InputStream).
</p>

<p>
  I solved this problem using a <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/io/PipedInputStream.html">PipedInputStream</a> and <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/io/PipedOutputStream.html">PipedOutputStream</a>. Reading from a PipedInputStream returns bytes written to the connected PipedOutputStream. Here was the Kotlin code I ended up with:
</p>

<code><pre>// Create a PipedInputStream; automatically close it at the end of
// the lambda
PipedInputStream().use { inputStream ->

  // Run the given lambda in a new thread
  thread {

    // Create a PipedOutputStream and connect it to the
    // PipedInputStream; automatically close it at the end of the
    // lambda
    PipedOutputStream(inputStream).use { outputStream ->
      generateCsv(outputStream)
    }
  }

  uploadToS3(inputStream)
}</pre></code>

<p>
  These classes come with a couple of gotchas. First, you should write to the PipedOutputStream and read from the PipedInputStream on separate threads. (Each class’s documentation clearly states this, so this isn’t so much a gotcha as a case of me not reading the docs closely enough.) If you read and write on the same thread, you might encounter a deadlock.
</p>

<p>
  The deadlock’s symptoms depend on whether your single-threaded code reads before it writes or vice versa. If it reads from the PipedInputStream first, it’ll hang forever waiting for something to write to the PipedOutputStream. However, if it writes to the PipedOutputStream first, you might not see any symptoms initially. In my case, I wrote a passing test that generated a small CSV and uploaded it to an S3 mock. However, when the code ran in production, it generated part of the CSV, then looped forever.
</p>

<p>
  The problem is buffering. PipedInputStreams buffer 1,024 bytes by default. Like I did, you might also wrap the former in a BufferedReader or the latter in a BufferedWriter, which default to using 8,192-byte buffers. As long as the data you write fit into the largest buffer in the stream, you won’t notice any problems. Writing won’t block because the buffer can hold all the written bytes. Then the PipedInputStream can read all the data you wrote. But as soon as you write enough data to fill the buffer, your write will block and you’ll encounter a deadlock.
</p>

<p>
  As the code above demonstrates, the solution is to read on one thread and write on another. That way, reading and writing can block without preventing the other operation from making progress.
</p>

<p>
  After realizing this, I encountered the second gotcha. My code initially called <code>generateCsv</code> on the main thread and <code>uploadToS3</code> on the thread created by <code>thread</code>. The issue is that, when <code>generateCsv</code> finishes, the main thread returns from the <code>use</code> block associated with the PipedInputStream. This closes the PipedInputStream even if <code>uploadToS3</code> is in the middle of reading from it. In my case, I noticed that the CSV file written to the S3 mock was truncated.
</p>

<p>
  To solve this problem, read on the main thread and write on the newly-created thread. This way, the PipedInputStream doesn’t close until <code>uploadToS3</code> has read everything from it.
</p>

<p>
  It took me a few hours to figure out what are in retrospect a couple of simple mistakes. My main takeaway is that I need to read documentation more carefully. I should also spend more time getting to know Java’s I/O primitives better.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/pipedinputstream-and-pipedoutputstream-gotchas/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">pipedinputstream-and-pipedoutputstream-gotchas</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Grayscale screens]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  About a year ago I noticed that a coworker of mine had configured his phone’s screen to display everything in grayscale. He told me his goal was to make the screen less interesting to look at, to reduce the temptation to spend a lot of time looking at it. That convinced me to also switch my phone to grayscale.
</p>

<p>
  A year in, I’m not sure if the change has had much effect. I still spend a lot of time on my phone. I’ve had more success reducing that amount of time by disabling or uninstalling apps I spend a lot of time on. But whenever I disable grayscale mode, I’m shocked by how vibrant and interesting the colours are, so I think it’s had at least a small impact.
</p>

<p>
  Today I installed <a href="https://github.com/laerne/desaturate_all"><code>desaturate_all</code></a>, a Gnome extension that enables grayscale mode for Ubuntu. I suppose my goal is the same: to make my laptop less interesting to look at. Mainly I hope I’ll interact differently with sites like Reddit. If I make their content less flashy and visually interesting, maybe I’ll spend less time on them.
</p>

<p>
  I’ve also considered purchasing a phone or a monitor with an e-ink screen. These screens both enforce grayscale (although colour e-ink displays are also available) and don’t strain the eyes as much as LCDs. I considered purchasing a Kingrow K1 e-ink smartphone, but was deterred by the lack of Google Play support and the difficulty of getting it shipped to Canada. Searching again, the Hisense A5 looks like a more promising option that I’ll have to investigate further.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/grayscale-screens/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">grayscale-screens</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Using Workman]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  Previously: <a href="/blog/learning-workman/">Learning Workman</a>
</p>

<p>
  On May 12, I completed my first lessons using the <a href="https://workmanlayout.org/">Workman keyboard layout</a> on <a href="https://www.keybr.com/">Keybr</a>. On May 25, I started practicing seriously, spending 15 minutes a day each day from then until June 11. By June 9 I’d learned all the new layout’s letter keys.
</p>

<p>
  As I thought I might in my last post, on June 13, I started practicing using <a href="https://www.typingclub.com">TypingClub</a> instead of Keybr. I hoped that typing real words and sentences only would help me build word-level muscle memory faster. TypingClub also trains me on capital letters and punctuation. Keybr can train you on these too, and more intensely than TypingClub: Every word can be capitalized or end with punctuation. However I thought I’d learn these keys more quickly by using them in real-world contexts.
</p>

<img src="typingclub-lesson.png" alt="A screenshot of a TypingClub lesson about African languages. The first two sentences of the passage are visible. The first sentence has already been typed. Letters typed correctly the first time are highlighted in green, those typed incorrectly and then correctly in yellow. A bar at the bottom shows my progress through the lesson.">

<p>
  TypingClub is an OK resource for those learning to type. It offers a full course in touch-typing but I skipped ahead to its advanced lessons, which involve typing a three-to-five-sentence biography of a person or summary of a concept. The website’s clearly aimed towards students: The lessons use a middle- or high-school reading level and some are about plagiarism and online bullying. It’s also focused on Western culture, with many lessons on American historical figures, authors, and politics. I found the lesson UI, which shows how fast you type each word and your speed and accuracy for the current lesson, pretty distracting and hid most of these UI elements using uBlock Origin. Overall TypingClub is useful but I imagine better services exist for adults.
</p>

<p>
  On June 23 I had a scare. As I wrote in my journal, “I thought I’d totally lost my QWERTY muscle memory. I did some typing practice, then switched back to QWERTY [...] and found it really difficult to type accurately.” Luckily, after an hour or so, my QWERTY muscle memory came back. This incident taught me not to practice Workman right before work. Another time I did so, I typed slower and less accurately than usual for most of the workday. By contrast, this morning I practiced Workman, then showered and went for a walk. I started work an hour after I finished practicing and had no trouble using QWERTY.
</p>

<p>
  I haven’t been as diligent about practicing daily with TypingClub as I was with Keybr. I missed a couple of days in mid-June and four last week (partly because I went on vacation without a computer). Still, I’ve increased my Workman typing speed by about 13 words per minute (wpm) in the past month:
</p>

<img src="typing-speed-graph.png" alt="A graph of my Workman typing speed over the past month. Each data point is the speed at which I typed when taking together all lessons completed on that day. A linear trendline with R2 = 0.655 goes from about 39 wpm on June 13 to about 52 wpm on July 10.">

<p>
  Unfortunately this is faster than my real-world typing speed. I find I type faster when I can always see the next letter I need to type, as with Keybr and TypingClub but not when typing a chat message. But the change in speed feels roughly accurate. I think a small amount of this increase comes from higher accuracy but most is from improved muscle memory, both at the three-or-four-letter sequence level and at the word level.
</p>

<p>
  My speed isn’t improving as quickly as I’d like, which is why on July 5 I started using Workman full-time on my personal computer. So far it’s been slow going. I still haven’t found a way to use the same keyboard layout across all programs. My current solution affects Firefox and Discord but not my terminal emulator or Ubuntu settings. As I discovered, it’s difficult to switch quickly between layouts, so I need to find a better solution. I also discovered that the Workman keymap I’m using has a couple of bugs: the Caps Lock key is bound to both caps lock and backspace, and the left arrow key doesn’t work at all. The keymap is open-source so I’ll contribute the fixes back to the original project if I fix these issues before finding a different way to use Workman on Ubuntu (a friend of mine suggested a programmable keyboard).
</p>

<p>
  I’m still a ways from using Workman at work. I’m currently relearning common shortcuts like opening and closing new tabs, and even copy and paste. More importantly, I haven’t figured out how to avoid disrupting my Vim muscle memory. I’ll definitely rebind HJKL (equivalents for the arrow keys) to YNEO (the letters on the Workman keyboard triggered by the same keys as HJKL on QWERTY). But should I also rebind often-used Vim keys like I, A, Y, and P so that they don’t change position, or should I relearn the positions and keep the mnemonic key bindings (Insert, Append, Yank, and Paste respectively)? I haven’t decided yet.
</p>

<p>
  In any case, I’ll keep using Workman, with the goal of using it at work too. It’s subjective and potentially biased, but this keyboard layout does feel easier on my hands than QWERTY. I typed this blog post using Workman: Here’s to many more.
</p>

<p>
  P.S.: Here are two fun facts. First, this whole process hasn’t affected my phone-typing muscle memory at all. (It makes sense: Typing Workman on a keyboard is much more like typing QWERTY on a keyboard than typing QWERTY on a phone.) Second, it’s quite difficult to type the word “QWERTY” using Workman… Someday I’ll build the word-level muscle memory for it.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/using-workman/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">using-workman</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[This blog has an RSS feed]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  I recently added an
  <a href="https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/rss.xml">RSS feed</a> to my
  blog, prompted by a friend asking if I had one. I write these posts in
  HTML. I don’t use a static site generator. So I assumed I wouldn’t be
  able to generate a feed using existing software. (Later, I realized
  there exist tools that build an RSS feed from a given webpage. I
  looked at one and saw the feed it built didn’t have anywhere near the
  format I wanted.)
</p>

<p>
  I wrote
  <a
    href="https://github.com/tbroadley/thomasbroadley.com/blob/35270f4/blog/rss/index.ts"
    >a small TypeScript program</a
  >
  to generate the RSS feed. It uses
  <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/htmlparser2"
    ><code>htmlparser2</code></a
  >
  to parse the posts and
  <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/rss"><code>rss</code></a> to
  generate the RSS feed from the contents.
</p>

<h2>The right tool for the job</h2>

<p>
  I soon realized <code>htmlparser2</code> wasn’t the easiest tool to
  use. The library uses a callback interface: It lets you provide
  functions that it then calls when it encounters opening and closing
  tags, text nodes, and other document features. It’s up to the code
  using the library to track its location in the parse tree.
</p>

<p>
  Instead, I could have used a library like
  <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/parse5"><code>parse5</code></a
  >, which parses the HTML into a JavaScript object and makes it easy to
  access elements with known locations in the parse tree. It’s a
  tradeoff, though: If I’d written the script using that approach, small
  changes in the layout of the HTML would have broken it. In fact, I
  think it would have been easiest to write this script using browser
  APIs like <code>Document#querySelector</code>. For that reason, maybe
  I should have used a DOM implementation like
  <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/jsdom"><code>jsdom</code></a
  >.
</p>

<h2>Parsing the posts</h2>

<p>
  In any case, solving this problem with <code>htmlparser2</code> was a
  fun challenge. I wanted to extract three pieces of information from
  each post: its title and creation date and the post body. First, I
  worked on extracting the title.
</p>

<p>
  I added callbacks for opening tags, closing tags, and text nodes.
  <code>htmlparser2</code> does a pre-order traversal of the parse tree:
  If you identify the calls to the opening and closing tag callbacks for
  a given element, any calls to the text node callback in between must
  be for text nodes inside that element. Each post’s
  <code>title</code> tag contains the title, so all I had to do was
  extract the text node inside that tag. Since each post only has one
  <code>title</code> tag, I did this by setting an
  <code>inTitle</code> variable to true when I saw an opening
  <code>title</code> tag, storing the contents of the text node seen
  when <code>inTitle</code> was true in a second variable, and setting
  <code>inTitle</code> to false on a closing <code>title</code> tag.
</p>

<p>
  I did something similar to extract the creation date, which is
  contained in a <code>p</code> tag with the class
  <code>timestamp</code>. The opening tag callback takes a map of HTML
  attributes as well as a tag name, so it was easy to recognize this
  particular <code>p</code> tag by its class. The closing tag callback
  doesn’t provide the tag’s attributes, but I realized I could set
  <code>inDate</code> to false on any closing <code>p</code> tag, since
  the paragraph containing the timestamp doesn’t have any paragraphs
  inside it.
</p>

<h2>Getting the post contents</h2>

<p>
  Extracting the contents of each post was more difficult. The body of
  each blog post lives in a <code>section</code> tag. It can contain
  HTML itself—so far I’ve mainly used <code>a</code> and
  <code>code</code> tags. However, <code>htmlparser2</code> doesn’t let
  you read the contents of a specific HTML element. It just calls your
  callback functions when it sees opening tags, closing tags, and text
  nodes. I needed to rebuild the HTML inside the
  <code>section</code> tag only using the information from these
  function calls.
</p>

<p>
  To keep track of whether it’s inside the <code>section</code> tag, the
  script uses an <code>inSection</code> Boolean variable, similar to how
  it keeps track of whether it’s inside the <code>title</code> tag. It
  appends any text it sees inside the <code>section</code> tag to a
  <code>content</code> string variable that starts off empty. When the
  script sees an opening tag inside the <code>section</code> tag, it
  uses the tag name and map of attributes to build a string containing
  an HTML opening tag, then appends it to <code>content</code>. This
  logic closes self-closing tags but leaves other tags open. On
  encountering a closing tag inside the <code>section</code>, the script
  appends a closing tag to <code>content</code>, as long as the tag
  isn’t self-closing. The pre-order traversal ensures the script appends
  tags and text to <code>content</code> in the same order it appears in
  the original post.
</p>

<h2>Generating the RSS feed</h2>

<p>
  Generating the feed was simpler. Each post lives in its own folder, so
  the script gets a list of those folders, reads and parses each post,
  adds an item to the feed for each parsed post, and writes the feed to
  an XML file. After running the script, I commit the updated file to my
  website’s Git repository and push to publish.
</p>

<h2>Why TypeScript?</h2>

<p>
  I wrote this script in TypeScript but didn’t benefit much from doing
  so compared to writing it in JavaScript. Most of the compile errors I
  encountered would have been runtime errors in JS, but the cause would
  have been equally obvious. On the other hand, I didn’t waste much time
  using TS. It didn’t take long to install <code>ts-node</code> and type
  definitions for the libraries I was using, and I don’t expect
  <code>ts-node</code> was much slower than Node for such a small
  script. Plus, I would have benefited more from TS with a different
  development environment. I wrote this script using Vim, without even
  TS syntax highlighting. If I’d used an IDE with type-aware code
  completion and integrated type-checking, or installed Vim plugins for
  those features, TS would have been an improvement over JS.
</p>

<h2>Why RSS?</h2>

<p>
  So why RSS? I’m a big consumer of RSS feeds myself and I know I’m not
  alone, even if they’re not as popular as they used to be. RSS is a
  simple way to share new content with people interested in your work.
  Of course, it’s not the only way. I could share my posts over Twitter
  or Facebook, but I started using RSS in the first place to get off
  social media. (A topic for another post.) Substack and Mailchimp make
  it easy to share content over email, but I like having full control
  over the distribution of my posts. I’d rather not give that control to
  a third party, at least for a passion project that I don’t plan to
  monetize, like this blog. I’d definitely consider using Substack for a
  paid newsletter to avoid integrating with a payment processor.
</p>

<h2>P.S.: Why not an SSG or a CMS?</h2>

<p>
  It’s also worth examining why I don’t use a static site generator or a
  CMS for my blog. I certainly could have built it more quickly using
  one of those tools. Well, again, I like having full control over my
  website, both its appearance and its code. A tool like Wordpress
  doesn’t give you that control without a lot of customization. I also
  appreciate that my website’s code is simple and human-readable.
  Finally, I enjoy solving problems and writing software. I don’t see
  the time spent working on projects like this one as wasted. I even
  enjoy the process of turning each post into an HTML document. It’s a
  good Vim exercise and the process somehow makes me feel more proud of
  my posts.
</p>

<hr>

<p>
  Edit: The day after publishing this blog post, I decided to move my
  posts into YAML files and generate both the HTML for them and my blog's
  RSS feed from those files. Each post shares a lot of code and it's
  painful to change something in all of them (e.g. adding a link to the header).
  Now that each post is based on a template HTML file, it's easy to make these
  kinds of changes. It's also a lot easier to parse YAML than HTML. And I still
  get to hand-edit each post's HTML! (Although I might look into generating them
  from Markdown instead.)
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/this-blog-has-an-rss-feed/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">this-blog-has-an-rss-feed</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Project retrospective: EDM Scraper]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  In 2016, I got into live music seriously for the first time. At first
  I found concerts by looking through long lists of ones in Toronto for
  artists I recognized. At the start of 2017 I decided to automate this
  process. Thus was born
  <a href="https://github.com/tbroadley/edm-scraper">EDM Scraper</a>: a
  service that sends mea daily email containing new concert listings
  near me.
</p>

<p>
  The project is a collection of Ruby scripts that scrape different
  webpages. To do the scraping, these scripts use the headless browser
  PhantomJS; the Capybara library, which can simulate interactions with
  many different browsers and is often used for Rails acceptance
  testing; and Poltergeist, a library that allows Capybara to interact
  with PhantomJS. Each script stores the scraped concert listings in a
  database. Finally, another script reads the database and sends me a
  digest of new and interesting concerts using the PostageApp
  email-sending service.
</p>

<p>
  My definition of “interesting” was nuanced, which was one reason I
  wasn’t satisfied with using Spotify or another service that lets you
  know about concerts for artists you follow. I particularly enjoy EDM
  shows, even when I don’t know the DJ well. I decided I wanted the
  service to email me whenever it found a new EDM concert. However, I
  also wanted an email when specific artists that I really liked, not
  limited to EDM producers, came to town. I created one scraper for a
  website with a comprehensive list of EDM shows in Toronto. I then
  added a second scraper for a website listing all Toronto concerts.
  This scraper only saves listings for concerts that match a list of
  artist names I’ve put together by hand.
</p>

<p>
  I decided to build EDM Scraper using Ruby because I’d previously used
  Capybara for end-to-end testing and scraping. I originally decided not
  to use Rails because I didn’t expect to use most of Rails’s
  functionality, but I now regret that decision. I did want to store
  concert listings in a database. I used ActiveRecord for this and found
  it more difficult than expected to integrate the library into the
  project. Instead, I should have let Rails handle the integration with
  ActiveRecord. I was also worried that setting up a Rails application
  would make it slower to start the project. In retrospect, this doesn’t
  make sense: the Rails CLI makes it easy to set up new projects.
</p>

<p>
  So far, I’ve only written tests for the logic-heavy parts of the
  project: parsing concert dates, deciding which artists to include in
  the email, and building the email itself. The scripts that scrape the
  web pages and send the emails don’t have automated tests. I found it
  easy enough to test those by running them on my computer. I set up the
  scripts so that they could either connect to the production PostgreSQL
  database, a local PostgreSQL database for development, or an instance
  of NullDB for automated testing. In fact, I often use the NullDB mode
  when manually testing scripts too. The database logic is centralized
  in an ActiveRecord model, so I don’t worry about bugs in how a
  specific script persists concerts.
</p>

<p>
  The nature of the project means that, if a script fails, the only
  symptom is not receiving an email, which I might not notice for a
  while. To remedy this, I wrapped each script in a function that would
  run the block passed to it, catching any exceptions thrown by the
  block and sending me an email if it did catch one. Of course, if the
  scripts can't email me, I still wouldn’t know that anything had gone
  wrong, but so far that hasn’t been a problem.
</p>

<p>
  Currently EDM Scraper runs on Heroku’s free tier. The free tier makes
  a lot of sense for this project because it’s mostly implemented using
  scheduled tasks with soft deadlines. It doesn’t matter if it takes an
  extra ten seconds for a free dyno to spin up. Eventually I did create
  <a href="http://edm-scraper.herokuapp.com">a simple webpage</a> that
  lists all future concert listings , but I don’t access it often enough
  to be bothered by the ten seconds I have to wait for the page to load.
</p>

<p>
  So far, I haven’t needed to put much effort into maintaining the
  project. A few times, one of my scrapers has balked at some new
  formatting on the page and I’ve had to adjust it slightly. I also
  added scrapers for shows in New York when I lived there in the summer
  of 2018, and more recently a scraper for virtual festivals occurring
  during the pandemic. Many of the commits in the project’s Git history
  are just adding more artists to my list. My next step for the project
  might be to fetch a list of artists I follow from Spotify, instead of
  maintaining the list by hand.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/project-retrospective-edm-scraper/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">project-retrospective-edm-scraper</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Learning Workman]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  Recently I’ve been learning how to type using the
  <a href="https://workmanlayout.org/">Workman keyboard layout</a>. I’ve
  heard many times that QWERTY isn’t very ergonomic. I decided to learn
  a new keyboard layout to see how it’d affect my typing speed,
  accuracy, and comfort, and because it seemed like an interesting
  challenge. I must admit I didn’t do much research into the other
  alternative layouts. Basically, Workman’s excellent website convinced
  me to try it.
</p>

<p>
  I’ve been practicing around 15 minutes a day for the past two weeks.
  I’ve considered practicing more, but honestly I don’t find the process
  that fun. Plus, I already spend a lot of time typing, using my phone,
  and playing the piano and bass, so I don’t want to put too much more
  strain on my hands.
</p>

<p>
  I’m using <a href="https://keybr.com">Keybr</a> to learn Workman. It
  teaches you to type using many short lessons, 20 or 25 words each by
  default, composed of a randomly-generated mix of real and fake words.
  The fake words are either short, English-like sequences of letters or
  portmanteaus of two real words. You learn one letter at a time, only
  moving onto the next letter once you’ve mastered the current one.
</p>

<p>
  I started using Keybr to improve my QWERTY typing but found it
  annoying to use. I think that’s because I have word-level muscle
  memory for that keyboard layout. The fake words threw me off because
  they didn't exist in my muscle memory.
</p>

<p>
  Keybr works well for learning a new keyboard layout, though. Because
  of the fake words, the lessons don’t force you to type any one word
  too often, but are still full of common sequences of two to four keys
  containing the letter you’re currently learning. My hypothesis is that
  word-level muscle memory is built on top of muscle memory for these
  sequences. While learning a new key, I first gain muscle memory for
  the sequences enabled by introducing that key. For example, I learned
  I and N before learning G, so the lessons only included words ending
  in “ing” once I started learning G. Besides these sequences, I also
  build muscle memory for words of four letters or fewer that contain
  the new key. I then develop muscle memory for longer words. I looked
  for studies on motor learning that agreed or disagreed with this
  observation but couldn’t find any.
</p>

<p>
  I noticed a couple of factors that made a given key easier or more
  difficult to learn. It’s easy to analyze them using this graph from my
  Keybr profile:
</p>

<img
  alt="A graph from my Keybr profile. The x-axis is the typing lesson number, from 1 to 307. Each key has a row on the y-axis, sorted vertically by the lesson I started learning it. Each intersection of a lesson and a key contains a small rectangle, ranging from red for low speed and accuracy to green for high speed and accuracy (or white if I didn't practice that key in that lesson)."
  src="./keybr-graph.png"
/>

<p>
  The graph’s x-axis is the typing lesson number. You can see I’ve done
  307 Workman lessons so far. Red sections represent lessons with lower
  speed and accuracy for that key, while green indicates higher speed
  and accuracy.
</p>

<p>
  I found it easy to learn letters that Workman and QWERTY assigned to
  the same key. Unfortunately, only three of the letter keys I've
  learned so far are in the same location: A, S, and G. The graph above
  demonstrates that I quickly learned A and S and haven’t lost that
  proficiency since. G has been more challenging, perhaps because it
  doesn’t appear in every lesson.
</p>
<p>
  It was also easier to learn letters that only showed up in short
  words. For example, in my first lessons for K, the letter appeared
  almost exclusively in three- or four-letter words like “take” and
  “ack”. According to the graph, it only took me a few lessons to learn
  K initially. However, when a later lesson reintroduced it in a longer
  word, I struggled to remember it.
</p>

<p>
  Finally, learning certain keys completely threw off my muscle memory
  for the keys I’d already learned. It was like my brain had to break
  down and restructure my existing muscle memory to take into account
  the new key.
</p>

<p>
  Take the R key as an example. It was one of the first six keys I
  learned. It only took me a few lessons to master it. However, my speed
  and accuracy for R have fallen several times while learning other keys
  (e.g. A and M). I’ve gone through a similar process of gaining and
  losing muscle memory with other keys, most dramatically D, H, and B.
</p>

<p>
  It’s frustrating to get less proficient at a key. I wonder whether it
  would have been faster to learn how to type all the keys at once
  instead of one at a time. I think I would have abandoned the process
  because of the steeper learning curve, though.
</p>

<p>
  So far, I’ve learned all the letter keys except for Z, X, Q, and J.
  After learning those, to help me build word-level muscle memory, I
  might switch from Keybr to a different typing practice tool that
  emphasizes typing real words and sentences. I might practice with
  <a href="https://github.com/tbroadley/gpt-2-github">a tool</a> I
  developed that uses GPT-2 to generate typing lessons based on a GitHub
  user’s PR comments. The goal of this project is to let me practice
  typing text that’s as similar to the text I’m typing on a daily basis
  as possible.
</p>

<p>
  I’ll also try out Workman at work and in my personal life. I found it
  easy to install the layout on Mac OS by following the instructions
  <a href="https://github.com/workman-layout/Workman/tree/master/mac"
    >here</a
  >. Ubuntu is more challenging. The GitHub repository I just linked to
  contains instructions for four different ways to enable Workman on
  Ubuntu. I don’t run <code>xfree86</code>, so that method isn’t an
  option. The <code>linux_console</code> and
  <code>xorg</code> approaches don’t work on my computer—I think they
  might only work on an older version of Ubuntu. The
  <code>xmodmap</code> approach enables Workman in Firefox but not in my
  terminal. I’ll have to keep investigating.
</p>

<p>
  I’ll write another post once I’ve determined if Workman helps me type
  faster, more accurately, or with less effort. Even if I go back to
  QWERTY, learning Workman has already paid dividends: The process has
  improved my QWERTY typing. I’ve started using the “correct” fingers on
  more distant keys. For example, I now use my right ring finger to type
  O and P, instead of my middle finger. I’m not sure how to quantify the
  impact of this, but I think it’ll slightly reduce the strain of
  typing.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/learning-workman/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">learning-workman</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unlocking SSH keys using pass]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  I use
  <a href="https://www.passwordstore.org/"><code>pass</code></a> as my
  password manager. It stores passwords and other secrets as
  GPG-encrypted files in a Git repository. I host that repo on GitHub
  and have clones of it on my work and personal computers. I store
  nearly all of my personal passwords in <code>pass</code>, including
  passwords for my GitHub SSH keys. I’ve gone through three ways of
  unlocking these SSH keys.
</p>

<p>
  I started by running <code>pass -c SSH/Ubuntu</code> to copy my SSH
  key’s password to the keyboard, running a Git command like
  <code>git push</code>, then pasting my password into the prompt. I
  wasn’t satisfied with how much typing this process required. Plus,
  sometimes I’d forget to copy the password to my clipboard before
  running the Git command. I’d have to Ctrl+C that command and rerun it
  after copying the password. Even though I used
  <code>ssh-agent</code> and wasn’t unlocking my SSH key that often, I
  decided to automate this process.
</p>

<p>
  My second method used a script I called <code>sshpass</code>. Here it
  is in its entirety:
</p>

<pre><code>#!/usr/bin/expect -f
set password [exec pass SSH/Ubuntu]

spawn ssh-add
expect "passphrase"
send -- "$password\r"
interact</code></pre>

<p>
  This is an <code>expect</code> script. According to
  <a href="https://linux.die.net/man/1/expect">its man page</a>,
  <code>expect</code> is “a program that ‘talks’ to other interactive
  programs according to a script”. In this case, the script instructs
  <code>expect</code> to store the output of
  <code>pass SSH/Ubuntu</code> in the variable <code>password</code>,
  then run <code>ssh-add</code>, wait for it to prompt for a password,
  and write the password to <code>ssh-add</code>’s stdin. For reasons I
  don’t totally understand, the <code>interact</code> command, which
  attaches the terminal’s standard streams to <code>ssh-add</code>’s, is
  necessary to let <code>ssh-add</code> finish running.
</p>

<p>
  Now, all I had to do was run <code>sshpass</code> before running a Git
  command, but I’d still sometimes forget to run <code>sshpass</code>.
  Finally, this week, I came across a third solution that addresses this
  issue on Linux, mainly based on
  <a
    href="https://blog.ona.io/technology/2020/03/02/using-password-manager-with-ssh.html"
    >this blog post</a
  >.
</p>

<p>
  First, I added <code>AddKeysToAgent yes</code> to my SSH configuration
  at <code>~/.ssh/config</code>. This causes <code>ssh</code> to add
  keys to <code>ssh-agent</code> when they’re unlocked. This is
  important because we’ll no longer be explicitly calling
  <code>ssh-add</code>.
</p>

<p>Then, I added the following to my <code>.zshrc</code>:</p>

<pre><code>eval $(ssh-agent) > /dev/null
export SSH_ASKPASS=~/ssh-pass-passphrase.bash
alias ssh="setsid -w ssh"
alias git="setsid -w git"</code></pre>

<p>
  This starts an instance of <code>ssh-agent</code>, then sets the
  <code>SSH_ASKPASS</code> environment variable. If this variable is
  set, when <code>ssh</code> needs a password to unlock an SSH key, it
  runs the script pointed at by the variable and uses the output as the
  password. Note that this only works if <code>ssh</code> isn’t run in a
  terminal. That’s the purpose of the aliases for <code>ssh</code> and
  <code>git</code>: <code>setsid</code> runs these programs in a new
  shell session that isn’t associated with the terminal in which I’m
  running <code>ssh</code> or <code>git</code>. The <code>-w</code> flag
  causes <code>setsid</code> to wait until <code>ssh</code> or
  <code>git</code> exits before exiting.
</p>

<p>
  <code>~/ssh-pass-passphrase.bash</code> is a script that writes my SSH
  key’s password to stdout:
</p>

<pre><code>#!/bin/bash
pass SSH/Ubuntu</code></pre>

<p>
  Now, I can run Git commands without worrying if my SSH key is unlocked
  beforehand. If it isn’t, <code>ssh</code> automatically calls
  <code>pass</code> to get my SSH key’s password and unlocks the key
  before Git runs the command.
</p>

<p>
  So far, this setup only works on Ubuntu on my personal computer. My
  next step is to get it working on Mac OS, so I can use it on my work
  computer too. After that, I’d like to look into ways to avoid spawning
  an instance of <code>ssh-agent</code> in every terminal I run this
  command in.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/unlocking-ssh-keys-using-pass/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">unlocking-ssh-keys-using-pass</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rate-limit right before allocating]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  At work last week, I built an API endpoint that allowed logged-out
  visitors to our website to create rows in a database table. I wanted
  to prevent bad actors from adding a bunch of nonsense data to the
  table, so I added rate-limiting based on the user’s IP address. I
  implemented the endpoint as follows: First, it checked the rate limit
  and responded with a 429 if the user had surpassed it. If not, it
  validated the user-provided request data and responded with a 400 if
  it found invalid data. If both checks were successful, it saved the
  valid data to the database.
</p>

<p>
  It was only by filling out the HTML form connected to this endpoint
  that I discovered a design flaw. When I submitted invalid data for the
  first time, I’d receive a 400. However, after quickly fixing the
  invalid data and resubmitting it, I’d receive a 429 and wouldn’t be
  able to submit the now-valid data until the rate limit expired. From a
  user’s perspective, this was a terrible experience: If they made an
  error while filling out the form, they’d have to wait several seconds
  each time they tried to correct it.
</p>

<p>
  I realized that I wanted to limit the number of requests per user that
  would actually create rows in the database, not the total number of
  requests. Therefore, I changed the endpoint to validate the request
  data, <i>then</i> check the rate limit. This way, the endpoint only
  rate-limits valid requests. Now users can submit many invalid requests
  in a short period of time while trying different ways to fix the
  invalid data.
</p>

<p>
  This problem has a mirror image. Suppose you were implementing an
  endpoint with a high CPU cost and wanted to prevent each user from
  making too many requests in a short period of time. Further, suppose
  you implemented the API endpoint to first construct a response to the
  user’s request, then check the rate limit. In this case, the rate
  limit has no effect: A user can still make a large number of requests
  to the endpoint and consume a lot of CPU, even though they receive
  429s for most of the requests. The solution is to rate-limit before
  performing the CPU-intensive operation.
</p>

<p>
  These problems point to a general principle. Rate-limiting prevents
  one user from using too much of a shared resource, e.g. database space
  or CPU. The principle is this: Rate-limit right before allocating part
  of that shared resource to a request. If you check the rate limit too
  late, the rate-limiting won’t effectively protect the resource. If you
  check it too early, you’ll end up rate-limiting requests that wouldn’t
  have consumed the resource anyway, which might be a poor experience
  for users.
</p>

<p>
  Edit (2020-05-30): A couple of my coworkers pointed out that this
  principle has tradeoffs. In the first example in this article, I added
  a direct call to a rate-limiter method to the endpoint. We wouldn't
  want to do that for every endpoint that adds rows to the database.
  Instead, we could implement a configurable database rate-limiting
  system that allows you to specify different rate limits for insertions
  to different tables. We might want to implement a similar system for
  each shared resource. Contrast this with a single system that only
  allows you to rate-limit the number of requests per endpoint. The
  former allows you to limit bad behaviour more aggressively without
  compromising user experience, but it might not be worth the extra
  complexity.
</p>

<p>
  A coworker also mentioned a second use for rate-limiting: preventing
  dictionary attacks, both on sensitive information, like passwords, and
  less sensitive information, like tokens that refer to database
  objects. I think it's possible to treat this as a special case of
  protecting shared resources by considering the search space as a
  shared resource, but I haven't fully worked out this metaphor yet.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/rate-limit-right-before-allocating/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">rate-limit-right-before-allocating</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A small mindfulness win]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  Yesterday I participated in a discussion group over voice chat. It was
  the first time in a couple of months that I’d had a real conversation
  with people I hadn’t met before. Making more friends is a goal of
  mine, but I often feel prevented from achieving that goal by social
  anxiety. Yesterday was no exception. When I woke up in the morning, I
  was already thinking about bailing on the discussion group.
</p>

<p>
  In the past, I’ve found that doing fulfilling solo activities helps me
  counteract this anxiety. So yesterday morning I did yoga, meditated,
  went on a bike ride to a park, cooked lunch, and sang. Even after all
  that, I was still feeling anxious about ten minutes before the
  meeting. As the meeting started, I saw the list of people in the voice
  chat room and felt intimidated by its size. I nearly let myself bail
  on the discussion group.
</p>

<p>
  Luckily, I took the opportunity to practice mindfulness. I took some
  deep breaths, closed my eyes, and focused on how I was feeling
  physically. I immediately noticed that my anxiety had manifested as a
  pit in my stomach. I focused on that sensation as well as I could and
  after a couple of minutes it mostly went away. I felt much calmer and,
  after a couple more minutes, I was able to join the voice chat room.
  I’m so glad I did. The discussion group was the highlight of my week.
</p>

<p>
  I hope I’ll remember to use this technique more in the future. I think
  I can apply it not just to social anxiety but also my tendency to
  procrastinate.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/a-small-mindfulness-win/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">a-small-mindfulness-win</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What would we do if we didn't do code review?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>
  Every company I’ve worked at enforces peer code review before merging
  and deploying a pull request. I’ve been thinking about ways to improve
  this process for a while. Today I asked myself: If developers didn’t
  do code review, what would they do to achieve the same results?
</p>

<p>
  First, we need to ask: What is code review for? I’ll divide its
  benefits into three categories. The first contains the benefits of
  using automated code review tools. Type checkers, linters, and code
  formatters aren’t the only tools in this space. We can also check that
  pull requests don’t reduce test coverage or introduce untested code
  paths. To some extent, we can automatically enforce naming and commit
  message conventions. Tools can flag misuses of language features, the
  language’s standard library, and other libraries. We can also use
  static analysis, benchmarking, and profiling to look for performance
  issues. There’s a lot of room for creativity here. For example, at
  Faire, we implemented a tool that indicates when a pull request
  increases the size of our main JavaScript bundle.
</p>

<p>
  The second category includes conventions and checks that require human
  reasoning. Reviewers check that a pull request satisfies the
  requirements of the feature it implements, that the code is
  well-tested, and that the tests correctly describe the expected
  behaviour. Reviewers also provide feedback on comments and
  documentation, and ask the author to rewrite or comment unclear code.
  Finally, I’ve seen reviewers question whether it makes sense to
  implement the proposed change at all.
</p>

<p>
  The third category contains the harder-to-quantify benefits of having
  more than one person look at each pull request. Developers feel
  ownership for the code they review and responsibility for bugs that it
  introduces. Code review is a great way to share knowledge, both from
  reviewer to reviewee and vice versa. It also means that at least two
  people should be familiar with every line of code in the codebase,
  reducing the team’s bus factor. Finally, to build a sense of
  solidarity, it’s important for developers on the same team to work
  together on a daily basis.
</p>

<p>
  Looking at the benefits in the second and third categories, I see a
  common thread: They’re also the benefits of pair programming. While
  pairing, the observer can give the same kinds of feedback on code
  quality and functionality that a reviewer does. Even better, the
  driver gets this feedback as they’re writing the code, making it
  easier to integrate into the pull request. And pairing might be a
  better way to achieve the fuzzy goals in the third category, since
  developers collaborate in-person or over a voice or video call rather
  than through text.
</p>

<p>
  I don’t think pairing should completely replace code review. It’s
  possible that both developers working on a pull request are too close
  to the code and could benefit from a third opinion. Also, I find
  pairing more draining than writing code by myself. Some companies
  enforce constant pair programming—I wouldn’t be happy in that
  environment and I don’t think I’m alone.
</p>

<p>
  In any case, at the companies I’ve worked at, I’ve spent much more
  time reviewing code than pair programming. For example, this week, I
  spent about 90 minutes pairing and at least five hours reviewing code.
  I wonder what’d happen if we changed that balance. Perhaps we could
  encourage more pairing by waiving the code review requirement for pull
  requests that were paired on. That’d be an interesting experiment to
  run someday.
</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://thomasbroadley.com/blog/what-would-we-do-if-we-didnt-do-code-review/</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">what-would-we-do-if-we-didnt-do-code-review</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>